<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The temple A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the fifth of August. 1624. By Tho. Adams.</title>
            <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836262</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836262</idno>
            <idno type="VID">521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 818:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The temple A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the fifth of August. 1624. By Tho. Adams.</title>
                  <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Mathewes for Iohn Grismand, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls Alley at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of: Five sermons preached upon sundry especiall occasions: London, 1626.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:521:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:521:1"/>
            <p>THE TEMPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon Preached at</hi> PAVLS Croſſe the fifth of Auguſt. 1624.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> THO. ADAMS.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Augustine Mathewes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. Mathewes</hi> for <hi>Iohn Griſmand,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley at the Signe of the Gunne. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:521:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:521:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR HENRY CAREY, Lord HVNSDON, Viſcount Rochford.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the many abſurdities, which giue vs iuſt cauſe to abhorre the Religion of the preſent Roman Church, this ſeemeth to me none of the leaſt; that they haue filled all the Temples vnder the commaund of their politike Hierarchy, with Idols: and changed the glory of the Inuiſible God, into the worſhip of viſible Images. They inuocate the Saints by them, yea they dare not ſerue the Lord without them. As if God had repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his vnchangcable Law; and in ſtead of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all worſhip by an Image, would now receiue no worſhip without an Image. I haue obſerued this one, among the other famous markes of that Synagogue; that they ſtriue to condemne that which God hath iuſtified, and to iuſtifie what he hath condemned. For the former; He hath preciſely directed our Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only by faith in the merits of Chriſt: this they vehemently diſpute againſt. For the other; He hath (not without mention of his Ielouſie) forbidden all worſhip that hath the leaſt tang of Idolatry: this they eagerly maintaine. What large Volumes haue they written againſt the <hi>Second Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment!</hi> as if they were not content to expunge it out
<pb facs="tcp:521:3"/>of their Catechiſmes, vnleſſe they did alſo <hi>Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticè</hi> contradict it to the whole world. They firſt ſet the people vpon a plaine rebellion, &amp; then make ſhew to fetch them off again with a neat diſtinction. Thus doe they pumpe their wits to legitimate that by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, which God hath pronounced a Baſtard by his definitiue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: as if the Papall <hi>Decrees</hi> were that law, wherby the world ſhould bee iudged at the laſt day. But who will regard a houſe of magnificent ſtructure, of honorable &amp; ancient memory, when the plague hath infected it, or theeues poſſeſſe it? And who, in their right ſenſes, will ioyne themſelues to that Temple, which after pretence of long ſtanding, ſtately building, and of many ſuch prerogatiues and royalties, is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be beſmeared with ſuperſtitions, and profaned with innumerable Idols? Why ſhould wee delight to dwell there, where God hath refuſed to dwell with vs.</p>
            <p>I publiſh this argument as no new thing to your Lordſhip: but, wherin your well experienced know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is able to informe mee. Onely I haue beene bold, through your thrice honoured Name, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this ſmall Diſcourſe to the world: emboldened by the long proofe I haue had of your conſtant loue to the Truth, and the gracious Pietie of your moſt noble Mother, the beſt encouragement of my poore labours on earth. The beſt bleſsings of God bee ſtill multiplied vpon her, your ſelfe, your religious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and your honorable Family: which is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally implored by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble Seruant. THO. ADAMS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:521:3"/>
            <head>THE TEMPLE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. COR. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>What agreement hath the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God with Jdols?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not fit, they ſhould bee too familiar or neare together in this world, whoſe portions ſhall bee ſo farre aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the world to come. The <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Goates</hi> are indeed now blended promiſcuouſly, and none can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them here, but hee that ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them hereafter: the right and left hand of the laſt Tribunall ſhall declare them. But they that be alien or oppoſite to vs in Faith and Profeſſion, are manifeſt, and we haue a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:521:4"/>frequent charge <hi>De non commiſcendo.</hi> Now the neerer this ill match'd coniunction, the more intolerable: the ſame boord, ill; the ſame bed, worſe; worſt of all, the ſame <hi>Temple.</hi> So the Apoſtle begins his dehor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Bee not vnequally yoked with vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers:</hi> ſo he ends it, <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idoles!</hi> Diuers ſeeds of graine in one ground, diuers kinds of beaſts in one yoke,
<note place="margin">Deuter. 22.</note> diuers ſorts of cloth in one gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were expreſſely forbidden vnder the Law: and ſhall ſeuerall Religions bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in one Church vnder the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>The abſurdnes of ſuch a mixture is here illuſtrated by many oppoſitions; the ſound of all which is Interrogatiue, the ſenſe Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue. <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Vnrighteouſneſſe, Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſſe, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Beliall,</hi> the <hi>Beleeuer</hi> and the <hi>Infidel;</hi> theſe can haue no ſocietie, no communion, no concord, no coniunction; and <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not by Art diuide theſe words, for they are diuided by nature. Now as <hi>Quae Deus coniunxit, nemo ſeparet,</hi> Thoſe things that God hath ioyned together, let no man put aſunder: ſo <hi>Quae Deus ſeparauit, nemo coniungat,</hi> Thoſe things that God hath put aſunder, let no man ioyne together. The ſcope of the Text, and the matter of my Diſcourſe, is to ſeparate <hi>Idols</hi> from the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:521:4"/>
               <hi>Temple</hi> of God; the holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> hath diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to my hands: they cannot agree in his ſentence, let them neuer agree in our practiſe: curſed is hee that goes about to compound this controuerſie. The <hi>Temple</hi> is holy, <hi>Idols</hi> prophane; it is not lawfull to mixe <hi>Sacra profanis.</hi> The <hi>Temple</hi> is for God, <hi>Idols</hi> for the Deuill: God and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill admit no reconciliation. Therefore as two hoſtile nations, after ſome treatie of peace, neither liking the propoſed conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, breake off in a rage, <hi>In hoc vterque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentimus, quòd conſentire nolumus,</hi> in this we both conſent, that we wil not conſent at all; ſo be it heere agreed, that no agreement can bee made. In compoſing differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man, betwixt family and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, betwixt kingdome and kingdome, <hi>Beati Pacifici,</hi> Bleſſed are the Peace makers. But in reconciling Chriſt and Behal, the <hi>Temple</hi> of God and <hi>Idols, Maledicti pacifici,</hi> Curſed are the peace-makers. Heere <hi>Bella geri placeat magnos habitura triumphos.</hi> God himſelfe in Paradiſe did firſt put the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, his Apoſtle hath heere giuen the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme, and hee deſerues a malediction that ſounds a retreat.</p>
            <p>But as no battell can be well fought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order, and martial array, ſo no diſcourſe can bee made profitable without ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. The <hi>Temple</hi> therefore wee will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:521:5"/>to be Gods Caſtle, and <hi>Idolatry</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion of it. This Caſtle is but one, Idols are many. The Champions that God hath ſet to defend his Caſtle, are eſpecially or principally Princes and Paſtors, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and the Miniſtery; the aduerſary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that fight againſt it bee the Deuils mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Souldiers. The Munition on the one ſide is the Diuine Scripture, the ſacred Word of God: the Engines, Ordnance, and Inſtruments of aſſault on the other ſide, are <hi>Idols,</hi> Traditions, and thoſe carnall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, wherewith the corrupt heart of man ſeekes to batter it. This Siege is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall, this feud implacable, the difference irreconcileable. Yet at laſt the warre ſhall end, with the ruine of thoſe enemies, in the triumph of the righteous, and to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glory of God?</p>
            <p>Now though this warre bee euery way ſpirituall, it is diuers wayes conſiderable. There is a materiall, and there is a myſticall <hi>Temple:</hi> there are externall, and internall <hi>Idols:</hi> there bee ordinary, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Souldiers. Euery Chriſtian, as hee is a <hi>Temple</hi> of God, ſo not without the aſſault of <hi>Idols:</hi> there is a ciuill warre, a Rebellion within him, wherewith hee is continually exerciſed. In this militant eſtate of the Church none are free: onely he that giues full allowance to his owne corruptions, is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:521:5"/>not a Temple of God, but a Synagogue of Satan; a ſinke of vncleanneſſe, rather then a Sanctuary of holineſſe. Thus from one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ariſe many particulars; and you will ſay, <hi>Behold a company;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 30.11.</note> as <hi>Leah</hi> ſaid of her ſonne <hi>Gad, a Troupe commeth.</hi> Yet all theſe branches haue but one root: they are but like the wheeles of a Clocke, taken a little in ſunder to view, then to bee put together againe. Let not their number diſcourage your attention. When a wealthy fauourite of the world ſent his ſeruant to beſpeake lodging for him, he told the Hoſt, Here will come to night the Lord of ſuch a Mannor, the Land-lord of ſuch a Town, the Keeper of ſuch a Forreſt, the Maſter of ſuch an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, the Lay-parſon of ſuch a Pariſh, a Knight, a Iuſtice of Peace, a Gentleman, an Vſurer, and my Maſter; Alas, anſweres the Hoſt, I haue not lodging for halfe ſo many: Bee content, replies the ſeruant, for all theſe are but one man. So if you diſtruſt your memories for roome to entertaine ſo many obſeruations, yet be comforted, for all haue but this one Summe, <hi>There is no agreement betwixt the Temple of God and Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Temple.</head>
               <p>That which was built by <hi>Salomon,</hi> was iuſtly called the <hi>Wonder</hi> of the world: a white and glorious Monument, ſet on the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:521:6"/>hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> inuiting paſſengers to ſee it, and amazing their eyes when they beheld it. It was of white Marble without, of Cedar and Gold within, all of the beſt, all beautifull, precious, durable. So magnificent was that holy Structure, that al nations haue admired it,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 48.2.</note> all times celebrated it <hi>Beautifull for ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ioy of the whole earth is Mount Sion.</hi> While the fauour of heauen was ſet vpon Ieruſalem, the ioy of the whole earth was mount Sion. It is fit, hee that made the world a houſe for Man, ſhould haue a houſe in this world made for himſelfe: neither could it be too coſtly, ſeeing all the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls that went to it were his owne. Euery rotten Cottage is too good for Satan, no Fabricke could be too ſumptuous for God. While his people dwelt in Tents, Himſelfe was content to dwell in a Tabernacle: in the flitting condition of Iſrael, hee would haue his owne houſe a moueable, that they might neuer remoue without him. But when their reſidence was ſetled in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, he would haue his Tabernacle turned into a Temple; that they dwelling where he appoynted them, Hee might alſo dwell among them. The former was for motion, the latter for reſt: the one for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, the other his ſtanding houſe. All this while God had but one Houſe at once: firſt the Tabernacle, then that gaue place to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:521:6"/>the Temple, and <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple being defaced, was ſupplied by <hi>Zorobabels.</hi> Now he hath many houſes, euen ſo many as there bee nations, as there bee congregations, as there bee perſons profeſſing Chriſt. Wee haue houſes of our owne, why ſhould not God haue his? A Prince hath more hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then one, why ſhould the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be abridg'd? A King in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can dwell but in one houſe at once, let God haue neuer ſo many, hee can at once fill them all. Hee hath a houſe of fleſh, ſo euery Beleeuer is his Temple: a houſe of ſtone, ſo this materiall one is his Temple: a houſe neither of fleſh nor ſtone, but imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, immortall in the heauens. And as Chriſt ſayes,
<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> that <hi>in his Fathers Houſe there are many Manſions;</hi> ſo in his Fathers militant Church there are many houſes.</p>
               <p>It were vaine to aske what God ſhould doe with a houſe, when wee conſider what we do with our owne: what, but dwell in it? But how God doth dwell in it, ſeemes to be a queſtion: ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>hee dwells not in Temples made with hands.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 17.24.</note> Indeed he dwels not in them, as wee dwell in ours. Our houſe defends vs, God defends his houſe: our houſe comprehends vs, God comprehends his houſe. Wee are onely within our houſes, and they are without vs: God is ſo within his houſe, that hee is alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:521:7"/>without it, elſewhere, euery where, yea his houſe is within him. When we are abroad, we cannot keepe our houſes; yea when wee are in them aſleepe, they ſerue to keepe vs. God can neuer be abſent from his, nor doth the keeper of this <hi>Temple</hi> euer ſleepe. Now euery materiall Temple, wherein the Saints are aſſembled, the truth of the Goſpell is preached and profeſſed, the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments duely adminiſtred, and the Lords Name is inuocated and worſhipped, is the <hi>Temple of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is it called <hi>His</hi> Temple, but for the teſtification of his preſence? When <hi>Cain</hi> ſtood excommunicated for murdering his brother, and might not come to the place appointed for Gods ſeruice, he is ſaid to be <hi>caſt out from the preſence of the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.16.</note> Some haue interpreted the like of <hi>Ionahs flying from his preſence;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionah 1.3.</note> that he fled from the place where the Prophets vſed to ſtand ready to beſent of God.
<note place="margin">Leuit. 10.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Nadab and Abihu dyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord;</hi> that is, before the Altar of the Lord. That which was done before the Arke or Altar, in the Tabernacle or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was ſaid to be done <hi>coram Domino.</hi> And yet too many come to the Temple with ſo little reuerence, as if they thought God were not at home, or did not dwell in his owne houſe. But the Lord is preſent in his Temple: in vaine ſhall wee hope to finde
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:521:7"/>him elſewhere, if we do not ſeek him here.
<note place="margin">Math 18.20.</note> 
                  <hi>I will bee in the midſt of you, gathered together in my Name:</hi> not any where, not euery where, but here. Indeed, no place excludes him, but this place is ſure of him: hee fills all places with his preſence, hee fills this with his gracious preſence. Heere hee both heares vs, and is heard of vs:
<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>Audit orantes, docet audientes;</hi> hee heares our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and teacheth vs our leſſons. No place ſends vp faithfull prayers in vaine, no place hath ſuch a promiſe of hearing as the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. It is the Lords Court of Audience, his Highneſſe Court of Requeſts. There humble ſoules open their grieuances, from thence they returne loaden with graces. Why are many ſo voyd of goodneſſe, but becauſe they are negligent of the publike deuotions? They ſeek not the Lord where hee may bee found, therefore deſerue to miſſe him where they pretend to ſeek him. Why ſhould they thinke to finde God in their Cloſets, while they care not to ſeeke him in his Temples? When wee need the helpe of our friend, do we tarry till we meet him by chance, or till hee come to vs, or ſhall wee not rather go home to his houſe? <hi>Peter and Iohn went vp into the Temple at the houre of Prayer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 3.1.</note> they thought it not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to pray in their priuate chambers, but ioyne themſelues with the Congregation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:521:8"/>as a Nauy Royall to tranſport their holy Merchandiſe to heauen.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 134.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift vp your hands in the Sanctuary, and bleſſe the Lord.</hi> Pure hands are accepted in euery place; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Sanctuary. What followes? <hi>The Lord that made heauen and earth, bleſſe thee out of Sion.</hi> Hee ſayes not, the Lord that made heauen, bleſſe thee vpon earth: nor, the Lord that made earth, bleſſe thee out of heauen: but the Lord that made heauen and earth, <hi>bleſſe thee out of Sion.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings come originally from heauen, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately through Sion. In the Temple let vs ſeeke, in the Temple wee ſhall finde thoſe precious treaſures and comforts of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Temple</hi> is not without ſome ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Beſides thoſe prophane Polititians, that thinke with one <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> that there is no vſe of Temples: or thoſe <hi>Maſsilians,</hi> who (as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> reports) did adde to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hereſies <hi>Templorum contemptum:</hi> or thoſe <hi>Pſeudo-Apoſtoli,</hi> that laughed at a Temple full of Suppliants, as a houſe full of fooles. Or thoſe that bee of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> mind, who to ſettle himſelfe in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Iſrael, diuerts the people from Gods houſe at Ieruſalem. In ſtead of that ſnowy &amp; glittering Temple, they ſhall haue two golden repreſentations. Sion is too farre off, theſe ſhall bee neere home: that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:521:8"/>is a tedious way of deuotion, theſe both compendious and plauſible.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiqu. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> As <hi>Ioſephus</hi> brings him in perſwading them; My good people and friends, you cannot but know that no place is without God, and that no place doth containe God; whereſoeuer we pray, he can heare vs; whereſoeuer we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hee can ſee vs: therefore the Temple is ſuperfluous, the iourney needleſſe, God is better able to come to you, then you are to goe to him. Beſide theſe, the Temple of God hath two kinds of foes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Anabaptiſts tell vs; that the old ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition hath made thoſe houſes fitter for Stables then for Churches; that they ought no more to be called <hi>Templa Dei,</hi> but <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla Idolorum;</hi> as they pretend, the Paſſeouer was called in thoſe corrupt times,
<note place="margin">Iohn 2.13.</note> not <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha Dei,</hi> but <hi>Paſcha Iudaeorum.</hi> By the ſame reaſon they would haue remoued all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe ſome haue abuſed their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments. But we ſay, though euill men abuſe good things, yet if a kingdome were not a lawfull State, <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> would neuer haue been Kings; for good men doe not vſe euill things. The Temple in Chriſts time was become a denne of theeues, yet euen then and there did hee ſend vp deuout and holy Prayers. It is a groſſe ignorance that cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt a fault that proceeds <hi>ex natura facti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Th.</hi> 1. <hi>qu.</hi> 41. <hi>art.</hi> 6.</note> and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:521:9"/>which proceeds <hi>ex abuſu boni:</hi> the former is <hi>malum ſimpliciter,</hi> the other is but <hi>malum per accidens.</hi> No man pulles downe his houſe, becauſe vncleanneſſe hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in one of the chambers. Let offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be remoued from the Temple, not the Temple demoliſhed becauſe of offences. <hi>The Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 21.43.</note> ſaith Chriſt; not quite taken away, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken from the Iewes. When GOD threatned the like to <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.28.</note> he did not meane to haue no more Kings, or to reduce it to the former ſtate of Iudges: no, onely the kingdome ſhall loſe <hi>Saul,</hi> but Iſrael ſhall not loſe the kingdome. It is a Maxime in nature, Things dedicated to God, are not to bee transferred to the vſes of men: a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in Philoſophy,
<note place="margin">Plato.</note> 
                  <hi>Quae rectè data ſunt, eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi non licet:</hi> and a prouerbe among our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, To giue a thing, and take a thing, is fit for the Deuils darling.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Sacrilegious,</hi> to whom God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, if they let his Temple ſtand; but for the maintenance of it, they will bee ſo bold with him, as either to ſhare halfe, or leaue him none. There bee many that pray in the Temple, who yet alſo prey on the Temple: as if a thiefe ſhould doe homage to that houſe in the day, which hee meanes to robbe in the night. But alas, why ſhould I touch that ſore which is all dead fleſh?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:521:9"/>or ſpeake againſt Sacriledge <hi>In orbe ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> among them that delight in it? Where Lawyers are feeed, hired, bribed to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Sacriledge, God and his poore Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may euen hold their peace. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would be ſpoken for Sions ſake, but I take this place and time for neither the right <hi>Vbi</hi> nor <hi>Quando.</hi> We know, <hi>Abigail</hi> would not tell <hi>Nabal</hi> of his drunkenneſſe, till hee was awoke from his wine. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe God to awake you from this intoxication, we may then find a ſeaſon to ſpeak to you. But God keepe you from <hi>Nabals</hi> deſtiny;
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.37.</note> that when this ſinne ſhall bee obiected to your Conſciences on your death-beds, your <hi>hearts</hi> doe not then <hi>die in you like a ſtone.</hi> One thing let me beg of you in the Name of him, whom you thus wrong: Howſoeuer you perſiſt to robbe the <hi>Temple</hi> of the due Salary, yet doe not ſtand to iuſtifie it. By imploring mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy perhaps you may bee ſaued, but by iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Iniury, you cannot but be loſt. As the French King, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt ſaid to a woman kneeling and crying to him for Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; Stand vp woman, for Iuſtice Iowe thee; if thou beg'ſt any thing, beg mercy. So if you requeſt any thing of God, let it bee mercy, for he owes you Iuſtice: and in this poynt, God be mercifull to you all.</p>
               <p>It was <hi>Dauids</hi> earneſt prayer, <hi>One thing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:521:10"/>haue I deſired of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 27.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and that will I ſeeke after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to behold the beautie of the Lord, and to enquire in his Temple.</hi> There are many that pray <hi>Dauids</hi> words, but not with <hi>Dauids</hi> heart. <hi>Vnum petij,</hi> one thing I haue deſired, <hi>De praeterito,</hi> for the time paſt: <hi>&amp; hoc requiram,</hi> this I will ſtill ſeeke after, <hi>de futuro,</hi> for the time to come: I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired it long, and this ſuite I will vrge till I haue obtained it. What? to dwell in ſome of the houſes of God all the dayes of my life, and to leaue them to my children after me: not to ſerue him there with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, but to make the place mine owne poſſeſſion. Theſe loue the Houſe of God too well, they loue it to <hi>Haue,</hi> and to <hi>Hold:</hi> but becauſe the Conueyance is made by the Lawyer, and not by the Miniſter, their Title will bee found naught in the end: and if there bee not a <hi>Nifi prius</hi> to preuent them, yet at the great day of vniuerſall Audite, the Iudge of all the world ſhal condemne them. By this way, the neerer to the Church, the further from God. The Lords <hi>Temple</hi> is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to gaine vs to him, not for vs to gaine it from him. If we loue the Lord, we will <hi>loue the habitation of his Houſe, and the place where his Honour dwelleth:</hi> that ſo by being humble frequenters of his Temple below, we may be made noble Saints of his Houſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:521:10"/>aboue, the glorious kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee the enemies to the Temple, whereof the firſt would ſeparate <hi>Dominum à Templo,</hi> the other <hi>Templum à Domino.</hi> they would take God from the Temple, theſe would take the Temple from God. Let mee conclude this poynt with two watch-words.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt concernes vs of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the wayters of the Temple. It hath been an old ſaying, <hi>De Templo omne bonum, de Templo omne malum:</hi> all good or euill comes from the Temple.
<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> Where the Paſtor is good, and the people good, hee may ſay to them, as <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Nonne opus meum vos eſtis in Domino, Are not ye my work in the Lord?</hi> Where the Paſtor is bad, and the people no better, they may ſay to him, <hi>Nonne deſtructis noſtra tu es in ſeculo,</hi> art not thou our deſtruction in the world? It is no wonder, if an abuſed Temple make a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered people. A wicked Prieſt is the worſt creature vpon Gods earth: no ſinne is ſo blacke, as that ſhall appeare from vnder a white Surpleſſe. Euery mans iniquitie is ſo much the hainouſer, as his place is holyer. The ſinne of the Clergy is like a Rheume, which riſing from the ſtomach into the head, drops downe vpon the lungs, fretting moſt noble and the vitall parts, till all the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:521:11"/>members languiſh into corruption. The lewd ſonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> were ſo much the leſſe tolerable, by ſinning in the Tabernacle. Their ſacrifices might doe away the ſinnes of others; no ſacrifice could doe away their owne. Many a ſoule was the cleaner for the blood of thoſe beaſts they ſhed; their owne ſoules were the fouler by it. By one and the ſame ſeruice, they did expiate the peoples offences, and multiply their owne. Our Clergie is no Charter for heauen. Such men are like the conueyances of Land, Eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and Inſtruments to ſettle others in the kingdome of heauen, while themſelues haue no part of that they conuey. It is no vnpoſſible thing, for men at once to ſhew the way to Heauen with their tongue, and lead the way to Hell with their foot. It was not a Iewiſh Ephod, it is not a Romiſh Cowle, that can priuiledge an euill doer from puniſhment. Therefore it was Gods charge to the executioners of his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.6. 1 Pet. 4.17. Iohn 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Begin at my owne Sanctuary:</hi> and the Apoſtle tells vs, that <hi>Iudgement ſhall begin at the houſe of God.</hi> and Chriſt entring into his Propheticall Office, began reformation at his Fathers houſe. Let our deuout and holy behauiour preuent this; and by our reuerent carriage in the Temple of God, let vs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the God of the Temple. It ſhould be our endeuour <hi>to raiſe vp ſeed vnto our elder
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:521:11"/>Brother,</hi> to winne ſoules vnto Chriſt. <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ceſſate lucrari Chriſto, qui lucrati eſtis à Chriſto.</hi> If Chriſt, while hee was vpon the Croſſe, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> had giuen mee ſome drops of his owne blood in a Violl, how carefully would I haue kept them, how dearely eſteemed them, how laid them next my heart? But now he did not thinke it fit to truſt me with thoſe drops, but hee hath intruſted to me a flocke of his lambes, thoſe ſoules for whom hee ſhed his blood, like whom his owne blood was not ſo deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: vpon theſe let mee ſpend my care, my loue, my labour, that I may preſent them holy Saints to my deare Lord Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other concernes all Chriſtians; that they beware, leſt for the abuſes of men, they deſpiſe the Temple of God. For as the Altar cannot ſanctifie the Prieſt, ſo nor can the vnholineſſe of the Prieſt diſhallow the Altar. His ſin is his owne, and cannot make you guiltie: the vertue and comfort is from God, and this is ſtill able to make you holy. When wee read,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.17.</note> that <hi>the ſinne of the Prieſts was great before the Lord, for men abhorred the offering of the Lord:</hi> this we all confeſſe, was ill done of the Prieſts; and I hope no man thinks, it was well done of the people. Say their ſinnes, yea their very perſons were worthy to be abhorred, ſhall men therefore ſcorne the Sanctuary, &amp; caſt that contempt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:521:12"/>on the Seruice of God, which belongs to the vices of man? This were to adde our owne euill to the euill of others, and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God becauſe he was offended. Cannot the faults of men diſpleaſe vs, but wee muſt needs fall out with God? Doe we not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him iuſtly to abhorre our ſoules, when we ſo vniuſtly contemne his ſeruice? Know, that he is able to ſanctifie thy heart, euen by the miniſtery of that man whoſe heart hee hath not yet ſanctified. The vertue conſiſts not in the humane action, but in the diuine Inſtitution. Wee ſay of the Sacraments themſelues, much more of the Miniſters; <hi>Iſti non tribuunt, quod per istos tribuitur:</hi> theſe doe not giue vs, what God doth giue vs by them.</p>
               <p>But this age is ficke of ſuch a wanton le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie, that wee make choyce of the Temple, according to our fancy of the Preacher: and ſo tye vp the free Spirit of God from blowing where he pleaſeth, that he ſhall be beholding to the grace of the Speaker, for giuing grace to the hearer. So whereas <hi>Paul</hi> ties Faith to hearing, they will tie hearing to Faith; and as they beleeue the holineſſe of the man, ſo they expect fruit of the Sermon. This is to make <hi>Paul</hi> ſomething, and <hi>Apollos</hi> ſomething; wheras <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe ſayes they are <hi>both nothing.</hi> God onely giues the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and who ſhall appoint him by whom
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:521:12"/>he ſhall giue it? Let the ſeed bee good, and the ground good, and the Lord will ſend fruit whoſoeuer bee the Sower. But while you make hearing a matter of ſport, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is too often become an exerciſe of wit. Words are but the Images of matter, and (you ſhall heare anon) it is not lawfull to worſhip Images. It dangerouſly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomes the Temple, when any thing ſhall bee intended there, but the glory of God, and gaining of ſoules to Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning <hi>the Temple;</hi> the next poynt I muſt fall vpon is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Jdols.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idol</hi> in Greeke ſignifies a reſemblance or repreſentation, and differs not from <hi>Image</hi> in Latine: both at firſt taken in a good ſenſe: but the corruption of times hath bred a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of words; and <hi>Idol</hi> is now only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the Image of a falſe god. Euery <hi>Idol</hi> is an Image, but euery Image is not an Idol but euery Image made and vſed for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous purpoſes, is an Idol. The Images of God are Idols; wherwith Popery abounds. An old man, ſitting in a chaire, with a triple Crowne on his head, and Pontificall robes on his backe, a Doue hanging at his beard, and a Crucifixe in his armes; is their Image of the Trinitie. This Picture ſometime ferues them for a god in their Churches,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:521:13"/>and ſomtime for a ſigne at thir tap-houſes: ſo that it is a common ſaying in many of their Cities, Such a Gentleman lyes at the Trinity, and his ſeruants at Gods head. This they ſeeme to doe, as if they would in ſome ſort requite their Maker: becauſe God made man according to his Image, therfore they, by way of recompence, will make God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mans Image. But this certainly they durſt not doe, without putting the ſecond Commandement out of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſmes, and the whole Decalogue out of their Conſciences.</p>
               <p>I intend no polemicall diſcourſe of this poynt, by examining their Arguments: that buſineſſe is fitter for the Schoole, then the Pulpit. And, O God, that either Schoole or Pulpit in Chriſtendome ſhould be troubled about it! that any man ſhould dare to make that a queſtion, which the Lord hath ſo plainely and punctually forbidden! Beſide the Iniquity, how grieuous is the abſurdity? How is a body without a ſpirit, like to a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without a body? A viſible picture, like an inuiſible nature? How would the King take it in ſcorne, to haue his picture made like a Weſell or a Hedgehog? And yet the difference betwixt the greateſt Monarch, and the leaſt Emmet, is nothing to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwixt a finite &amp; an infinite. If they alledge with the Anthropomorphites, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:521:13"/>the Scripture attributes to God hands, and feet, and eyes: why therefore may they not repreſent him in the ſame formes? But we ſay, the Scripture alſo ſpeaks of his couering vs with the ſhadow of his wings; why ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they not paint him like a Bird with feathers? If they ſay, that he appeared to <hi>Daniel</hi> in this forme, becauſe hee is there called the <hi>Ancient of dayes:</hi> wee anſwere, that Gods Commandements, and not his apparitions, be rules to vs: by the former we ſhall be iudged, and not by the latter. It is mad Religion, to neglect what he bids vs doe, and to imitate what he hath done: as if we ſhould deſpiſe his Lawes, and goe about to counterfeit his thunder. God is too infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite for the comprehenſion of our ſoules, why ſhould we then labour to bring him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the narrow compaſſe of bords &amp; ſtones? Certenly, that ſhould not be <hi>Imaged,</hi> which cannot be <hi>Imagined.</hi> But Chriſt was a man, why may not his Image be made? Some anſwer, that no man can make an Image of Chriſt, without leauing out the chiefe part of him, which is his Diuinitie. It was the Godhead vnited to the manhood, that makes him Chriſt: ſure this cannot be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But why ſhould wee make Chriſts I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage without Chriſts warrant? The Lord hath forbidden the making of any Image, whether of things in heauen, where Chriſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:521:14"/>is; or of things on earth, where Chriſt was; to worſhip them. Now till God reuoke that precept, what can authoriſe this practice?</p>
               <p>Their Images of the Saints, employed to ſuch religious purpoſes, make them no leſſe then <hi>Idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers.</hi> It is a ſilly ſhift to ſay, the honor done to the Images, reflects vpon the repreſented Saints. When they cloath an Image, is the Saint ere the gayer or warmer? when they offer to an Image, is the Saint ere the richer? When they kneele to an Image, the Saint eſteemes himſelfe no more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, then the King holds himſelfe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, when a man ſpeaks to his picture be fore his face. Therefore ſome of them are driuen to confeſſe plainly, that the Image is worſhipped for it ſelfe. But could the Saints in heauen be heard ſpeak vpon earth, they would diſclaime that honour, which is preiudiciall to their Maker. As <hi>Caluin</hi> is not afraid to ſay of the bleſſed Virgin, that ſhee would hold it leſſe deſpite done to her, if they ſhould pull her by the haire of the head, or trample her in the dirt, then to ſet her in riuality with her Sonne and God and Sauiour. But they tell vs, that they worſhip not the Images of falſe Gods, as did the Pagans; but onely the Images of Gods owne ſeruants, and choiſe friends. But will the iealous God endure this, that his honor be taken from him, vpon condition it be not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:521:14"/>beſtowed vpon his enemies, but on his friends? <hi>Idolatry</hi> is called <hi>Adultery</hi> in the Scriptures: and ſhall a woman quit her ſelfe from offence, becauſe though ſhe doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery, yet it is with none but her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands friends? Is this done in a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or in loue to Chriſt? It is but a bad excuſe of a wife, to ſay that ſhee exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loues her husband, therefore muſt haue ſome other man to kiſſe and embrace in his abſence, and all this in loue to her husband.</p>
               <p>Wee are all by nature prone to <hi>Idolatrie:</hi> when we were little children, we loued ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies: and being growne men, we are apt to loue Images. And as Babies be childrens I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, ſo Idols &amp; Images be mens Babies. It ſeemes that Idols are fitteſt for Babes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo the Apoſtle fits his caution,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Babes keepe your ſelues from Idols.</hi> As all our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge comes by ſenſe, ſo we naturally deſire a ſenſible obiect of deuotion: finding it ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to ſee Pictures, then to comprehend Doctrines, and to forme prayers to the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of men, then to forme man to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God.</p>
               <p>Nor can they excuſe themſelues from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, by ſaying they put their confidence in God, not in the Images of God. For when the Iſraelites had made their golden Calfe, and danced about it, one calfe about another; they were not ſuch beaſts, as to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:521:15"/>thinke that beaſt their God. But ſo can Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition beſot the mind, that it makes vs not men, before it can wake vs Idolaters. What doe they ſay?
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Make vs gods that ſhall go before vs.</hi> Euery word is wicked, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, ſenſles. 1. They had ſeene the power of God in many miraculous deliuerances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes; the voice of God had ſcarce yet done thundering in their eares: he had ſaid, <hi>I am Iehouah, thou ſhalt haue no other gods;</hi> and this they trembling heard him ſpeake out of the midſt of the flames: and yet they dare ſpeake of <hi>another god.</hi> 2. The ſingular number would not ſerue them, make vs <hi>gods.</hi> How many gods would they haue? Is there any more then one? 3. <hi>Make</hi> vs gods; and were not they ſtrange gods that could bee <hi>made?</hi> In ſtead of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging God their <hi>Maker,</hi> they command the <hi>making</hi> of gods. 4. This charge they put vpon <hi>Aaron,</hi> as if he were able to make a god? <hi>Aaron</hi> might helpe to ſpoyle a man, either himſelfe or them, but hee could not make a man, not one haire of a man, much leſſe a god: and yet they ſay to him, <hi>Make vs gods.</hi> 5. And what ſhould theſe gods doe? <hi>Goe before vs?</hi> Alas, how ſhould they goe, that were not able to ſtand? how goe before others, that could not moue themſelues? Oh the blockiſhnes of men, that make blocks to worſhip! Otherwiſe, how
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:521:15"/>could they that are the Images of God, fall downe before the Images of creatures.
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 13.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For health, they call vpon that which is weake: for life, they pray to that which is dead: and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous iourney they beg of that which cannot ſet a foot forward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet as their ſinne was bad enough, let not our vncharitableneſſe make it worſe. Let vs not thinke them ſo vnreaſonable, as to thinke that Calfe a God; or that the Idoll which they made to day, did bring them out of Egipt three moneths before. It was the true God they meant to worſhip in the Calfe, and yet (at the beſt) euen that Idolatry was damnable. So charitie bids vs hope of the Papiſts, that they doe not take that bord or ſtone for their God, yet withall wee find that God doth take them for Idolaters. They tell vs (with a new diſtinction) that they forbid the people, to giue Diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to Images: but we ſay, they had better forbid the people to haue Images. A blocke lies in the high way, and a watchman is ſet by it to warne the Paſſengers; Take heed, heere is a blocke. But how if the watchman fall a ſleepe? Whether is the ſafer courſe, quite to remoue the blocke out of the way, or to truſt the paſſengers ſafetie vpon the watchmans vigilancie? As for their watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, commonly they are as very Images as the Images themſelues: and how ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:521:16"/>one blocke remoue another? When <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> had ſet vp his two Idols in Iſrael, hee rakes vp his Prieſts out of the common kennell; the baſeſt of the people were good enough for ſuch a baſtard deuotion: wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den prieſts were fit enough to wayt vpon golden Deities. So when <hi>Micah</hi> had made him a coſtly Idol, he hires him a beggerly Leuite. No otherwiſe did the Painter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelfe, for drawing the Images of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> too ruddy and high coloured in the face; that howſoeuer they were while they liued, pale with faſting and preaching, yet now they muſt needs become red with bluſhing at the errors and ignorance of their ſucceſſors; for ſuch with a lowd noyſe they giue themſelues out to be.</p>
               <p>To conclude, if it were as eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince Idolaters, as it is to confound &amp; tread downe their <hi>Idols,</hi> this labour of Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had bin well ſpared, or were ſoone en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But if nothing can reclaime them from this ſuperſtitious practice, let them reade their fearefull ſentence. Their place ſhall be <hi>without,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.18. Eſa. 1.31.</note> 
                  <hi>among the dogs,</hi> and thoſe deſperate ſinners vncapable of forgiuenes. <hi>The ſtrong,</hi> the Idol which they made their ſtrength, <hi>ſhall bee as towe, and the maker</hi> or worſhipper <hi>thereof as a ſparke, and they ſhall both burne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> in euerlaſting fire, <hi>and none ſhal quench them.</hi> Now the Lord open their eyes to ſee,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:521:16"/>and ſanctifie their hearts to yeeld, that <hi>there is no agreement betwixt the Temple of God and Idols:</hi> which is the next point, whereof I ſhall ſpeake with what breuitie I can, and with what fidelitie I ought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>No agreement.</head>
               <p>There bee ſome points which the wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paſſions of men haue left further aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then they found them; about which there needed not haue bin ſuch a noyſe. But things that are in their owne natures contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and oppoſed by the ordinance of God, can neuer be reconciled. An enemy may be made a friend, but enmity can neuer bee made friendſhip. The ayre that is now light, may become darke: but light can neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come darkneſſe. Contraries in the abſtract are out of all compoſition. The ſicke body be recouered to health, but health can neuer be ſicknes. The ſinner may be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but ſinne can neuer become righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Fire and water, peace and warre, loue and hatred, truth and falſhood, faith and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, Religion and Idolatry, can neuer be made friends: there <hi>can bee no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Temple of God and Idols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God is <hi>Ens entium,</hi> All in all: an <hi>Idol is nothing in the world,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: now <hi>All</hi> and <hi>Nothing</hi> are moſt contrary. Idolatry quite takes away Faith, a fundamentall part
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:521:17"/>of Chriſtian religion: for an Idol is a thing viſible,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> but <hi>Faith is of things inuiſible.</hi> The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol is a falſe euidence of things ſeene, Faith is a true euidence of things not ſeen. Beſides, God can defend himſelfe, ſaue his friends, plague his enemies:
<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> but Idols <hi>nec hoſtes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcindere poſſunt quaſi dij, nec ſe abſcondere quaſi homines;</hi> they can neither reuenge themſelus on prouokers, like gods; nor hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from iniurers, like men.</p>
               <p>The fooliſh Philiſtims thought that the ſame houſe could hold both the <hi>Arke</hi> &amp; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.3.</note> as if an inſenſible Statue were a fit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for the liuing God. In the morning they come to thanke <hi>Dagon</hi> for the victory, and to fall downe before him, before whom they thought the God of Iſrael was fallen: and loe, now they find the keeper flat on his face before the priſoner. Had they formerly of their own accord, with awfull reuerence, laid him in this poſture of an humble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; yet God would not haue brooked the indignity of ſuch an entertainment. But ſeeing they durſt ſet vp their Idol cheeke by cheeke with their Maker, let them goe read their folly in the Temple floore, &amp; confeſſe that hee which did caſt their god ſo low, could caſt them lower. Such a ſhame doth the Lord owe all them, which wil be making matches betwixt him and <hi>Belial.</hi> Yet they conſider not, how ſhould this God raiſe vs,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:521:17"/>who is not able to ſtand, or riſe himſelf? Strange they muſt confeſſe it, that whereas <hi>Dagon</hi> was wont to ſtand, and themſelues to fall down; now <hi>Dagon</hi> was fallen down, and themſelues ſtood; &amp; muſt help vp with their owne god. Yea, their god ſeemes to worſhip them on his face, and to craue that ſuccour from them, which he was neuer able to giue them. Yet in his place they ſet him againe; and now lift vp thoſe hands to him, which helped to lift him vp; and proſtrate thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to him, before whom he lay proſtrate. So can Idolatry turne men into the ſtockes and ſtones which they worſhip: <hi>They that make them, are like vnto them.</hi> But will the Lord put it vp thus? No, the next fall ſhall burſt it to pieces; that they may ſenſibly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, how God ſcornes a Competitor, and that there is <hi>no agreement</hi> betwixt <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>Idols.</hi> Now what is the difference betwixt the Philiſtims and Papiſts? The Philiſtims would ſet God in the Temple of <hi>Idols,</hi> the Papiſts would ſet <hi>Idols</hi> in the Temple of God. Both agree in this, that they would make God and Idols <hi>agree</hi> together. But <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> found to his coſt,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.7</note> that <hi>an Idol</hi> might not be indured <hi>in the houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How vaine then, are the endeuours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile our church with that of <hi>Rome;</hi> when God hath interpoſed this barre, there is <hi>No agreement</hi> betwixt him and Idols? Either
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:521:18"/>they muſt receiue the Temple without I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, or we muſt admit Idols with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or this compoſition cannot be. There is a contention betwixt Spaine &amp; the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers, concerning the right of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: but ſhould not the Inhabitants well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the coaſts, the raging ſea would ſoone determine the controuerſie, and by force of her waues take it from them both. There is a conteſtation betwixt vs and the Pontifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which is the true Church: but ſhould not wee in meane time carefully defend the Faith of Chriſt againſt Idols, Superſtition would quickly decide the buſines, and take the poſſeſſion of truth from vs both. A proud &amp; peruerſe ſtomach keeps them from yeelding to vs: God and his holy word for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids our yeelding to them: they will haue Idols or no Temple, we wil haue the Temple and no Idols: now till the agreement bee made betwixt the Temple and Idols, no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement can be hoped betwixt vs &amp; them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Paul ſay vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>that if ye be circumciſed, Christ ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> He that would not endure a <hi>little leauen in the lumpe,</hi> what would hee haue ſaid of a little poyſon? If <hi>Moſes</hi> ioyned with Chriſt, the ceremoniall Law with the Goſpell, were ſo offenſiue to him; how would hee haue brooked Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> light and darknes, righteouſnes and vnrighteouſnes, the cup of the Lord and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:521:18"/>the cup of deuils, the Table of the Lord, and the table of deuils, the Temple of God and Idols? In the tuning of an Inſtrument, thoſe ſtrings that be right we meddle not with, but ſet the reſt higher or lower, ſo as they make a proportion &amp; harmony with the former. The ſame God who of his gracious mercy, hath put vs in the right &amp; vniarring harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of truth, bring them home in true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to vs, but neuer ſuffer vs to fall back vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Hitherto the contention between vs hath not been for circumſtance, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; not for the bounds, but for the whole Inheritance: whether God or man, grace or nature, the bloud of Chriſt or the milke of <hi>Mary,</hi> the written Canon or vnwritten Tradition, Gods ordinance in eſtabliſhing Kings, or the Popes vſurpation in depoſing them, ſhall take place in our conſciences, and be the rule of our faiths and liues.</p>
               <p>We haue but one Foundation, the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble word of God: they haue a new founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the voice of their Church, which they equalize in preſumption of certaintie with the other. Wee haue but one Head, that is Chriſt; they haue gotten a new head, &amp; dare not but beleeue him, whatſoeuer Chriſt ſaies. <hi>Sponſus Eccleſiae noſtrae Chriſtus,</hi> Chriſt is our husband: they haue a new husband. While Rome was a holy Church, ſhe had a holy husband: but now as Chriſt ſaid to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:521:19"/>woman of Samaria,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> 
                  <hi>He whom thou now haſt, is not thine husband:</hi> ſo he whom the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts haue now got, is an adulterer, he is no husband. So that here is Foundation againſt foundation, Head againſt head, Husband a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt adulterer, Doctrine againſt doctrine, Faith againſt vnbeliefe, Religion againſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, the Temple of God againſt Idols; and all theſe ſo diametrally oppoſed, that the two Poles ſhall ſooner meet, then theſe be reconciled. <hi>Michael</hi> and the Dragon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree in one Heauen, nor the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon</hi> in one houſe, nor <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> in one wombe, nor <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> in one Bath, nor the cleane and the leprous in one camp, nor truth and falſhood in one mouth, nor the Lord and Mammon in one heart, nor religion &amp; ſuperſtition in one kingdom, nor God and Idols in one Temple. The ſilly old Hermite was ſory, that God and the Deuill ſhould be at ſuch odds, and he would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make them friends: but the Deuill bad him euen ſpare his labour, for they two were euerlaſtingly fallen out. No leſſe vaine a buſines doth that man attempt, that would worke an <hi>agreement betwixt the Temple of God and Idols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I take leaue of this point with a caution. Flie the places of infection, come not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſmoke of Idols, leſt it ſmother the zeale of Gods Temple in your hearts. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:521:19"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> cals for gods; but why ſhould this god of theirs be faſhioned like a <hi>Calfe?</hi> What may bee the reaſon of this ſhape? Whence had they the originall of ſuch an Idol? Moſt likely in Egypt: they had ſeen a blacke Calfe with white ſpots worſhipped there. This Image ſtil ran in their minds, and ſtole their hearts, &amp; now they long to haue it ſet vp before their eyes. Egypt wil not out of their fancies: when they wanted meat, they thought of the Egyptian fleſh pots: now they want <hi>Moſes,</hi> they thinke of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Idols. They brought gold out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt; that very gold was contagious: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eare-rings and Iewels of Egypt are fit to make Idols. The Egyptian burdens made them run to the true God, the Egyptian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples led them to a falſe god. What meane our wanderers by running to Rome &amp; ſuch ſuperſtitious places, vnleſſe they were weary of the Church of God, &amp; would fetch home Idols? If it were granted, that there is ſome little truth among them, yet who is ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as to ſeeke his corne among a great heap of chaffe, and that far off; who may haue it at home, winnowed and clenſed to his hand?</p>
               <p>The very ſight of euill is dangerous, and they bee rare eyes that doe not conuey this poiſon to our hearts. I haue heard of ſome, that euen by laboring in the Spaniſh galleys, haue come home the ſlaues of their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:521:20"/>Egypt was alwayes an vnlucky place for Iſrael, as Rome is for England. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoiourned there, and they brought home one <hi>Calfe: Ieroboam</hi> ſoiourned there, and he brought home <hi>Two calues:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 17.</note> an old woman (in all likelihood) had ſoiourned there, and ſhee brought home a great many. The Romiſh Idols haue not the ſhape of calues, they haue the ſenſe and meaning of thoſe calues: and to fill the Temple full of Calues, what is it but to make Religion guilty of
<note place="margin">* Non-ſence.</note> Pulls?</p>
               <p>Conſider it well, ye that make no ſcruple of ſuperſtitious aſſemblies; it will bee hard for you to dwell in a Temple of Idols vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted. Not to ſinne the ſins of the place we liue in, is as ſtrange, as for pure liquor tunn'd vp in a muſty veſſel, not to ſmel of the caske. Egypt will teach euen a <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to ſweare: a <hi>Peter</hi> will learne to curſe in the high Prieſts Hall. If we be not ſcorch'd with the fire of bad company, we ſhall be ſure to be black'd with the ſmoke. The ſoundeſt body that is, may be infected with a contagious ayre. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a man may trauel through <hi>Ethiopia</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed, but he cannot dwell there without a complexion diſcoloured. How hath the common practiſe of others brought men to the deuilliſh faſhion of ſwearing, or to the bruitiſh habit of drinking, by their owne confeſſions? Superſtition, if it haue once got a ſecret liking of the heart, like the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:521:20"/>plague will hang in the very clothes; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long concealement, breake forth in an vnlook'd for infection. The Iſraelites, after all their ayring in the wilderneſſe, will ſtill ſmell of Egypt. We read God ſaying,
<note place="margin">Math. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of Egypt haue I called my Sonne.</hi> That God did call his Sonne out of Egypt, it is no wonder: the wonder is that hee did call him into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. It is true, that Egypt could not hurt Chriſt: the King doth not follow the Court, the Court waits vpon the King: whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Chriſt was, there was the Church. But be our Iſraelites ſo ſure of their ſonnes, when they ſend them into Egypt, or any ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious places? It was their preſumption to ſend them in, let it bee their repentance to call them out.</p>
               <p>The familiar ſocietie of orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians with miſ-beleeuers, hath by God euer been moſt ſtrictly forbidden: and the neerer this coniunction, the more dangerous, and diſpleaſing to the forbidder. No man can chuſe a worſe friend, then one whom God holds his enemy. When Religion and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition meet in one bed, they commonly produce a mungrell generation.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.3.</note> If <hi>Dauid</hi> marry <hi>Maachah,</hi> their iſſue proues an <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> If <hi>Salomon</hi> loue idolatrous women, here is enough to ouerthrow him with all his wiſdome. Other ſtrange women only tempt to luſt, theſe to miſ-religion; and by ioyning
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:521:21"/>his heart to theirs, hee ſhall diſioyne it from God. One Religion matching with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not ſeldome breed an Atheiſt, one of no religion at all. I doe not ſay, this is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of diuorce after it is done, but of reſtraint before it is done. They may be <hi>one fleſh,</hi> though they be not <hi>one ſpirit.</hi> The difference of religion or vertue makes no diuorce here, the great Iudges ſentence ſhall doe that heereafter. And the beleeuing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is neuer the further from heauen, though hee cannot bring his vnbeleeuing wife along with him. The better ſhall not carry vp the worſe to heauen, nor the worſe pull downe the better to hell. <hi>Quod fieri non debuit, factum valet.</hi> But now, is there no tree in the Garden, but the forbidden? none for me to loue, but one that hates the truth? Yes, let vs ſay to them in plaine fidelitie, as the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> did to the <hi>Shichemites</hi> in diſſembling policie;
<note place="margin">Gene. 34.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee cannot giue our ſiſter to a man that is vncircumciſed:</hi> either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you to vs in the truth of our Religion, or wee will not conſent to you in the league of our Communion.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> calls this a plaine deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Chriſt. Hee that eateth of the meate offered to Idols, <hi>Guſtu negauit Chriſtum,</hi> hath denied Chriſt with his taſting. If hee but handle thoſe things with delight, <hi>Tactu ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gauit Chriſtum,</hi> hee hath denied Chriſt with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:521:21"/>his touching. Though hee touch not, taſte not, yet if he ſtand to looke vpon the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with patience, <hi>Viſu negauit Chriſtum,</hi> hee hath denied Chriſt with his eyes. If he liſten to thoſe execrable charmes, <hi>Auditu negauit Chriſtum,</hi> hee hath denyed Chriſt with his eares. Omitting all theſe, if he doe but ſmell to the Incenſe with pleaſure, <hi>O doratu nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit Chriſtum,</hi> hee hath denied Chriſt with his ſmelling It is ſaid of the Iſraelites, <hi>Commiſti ſunt inter gentes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 106.35</note> 
                  <hi>They were mingled among the Heathen.</hi> What followed? Preſently, <hi>they learned their works.</hi> The reaſon why the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen returned not to <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, is giuen by ſome, becauſe it met with a dead carkaſe by the way. Why doe we pray, <hi>Deliuer vs from euill;</hi> but that wee imply, (beſides all other miſchiefes) there is an infectious power in it to make vs euill? Let vs doe that wee pray, and pray that wee may doe it. Yea Lord, free vs from Egypt, eſtrange vs from Rome, ſeparate vs from Idols, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euill, <hi>For thine is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farre we haue taken a literall ſuruey of the Text; concerning the materiall Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, externall or obiectuall Idols, and the impoſſibilitie of their agreement. Now to come neerer home to our ſelues in a morall Expoſition: here firſt</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:521:22"/>
               <head>The Temple of God</head>
               <p>Is the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt; and they are ſo like, that we often interchange the tearmes, calling a Temple the Church, &amp; the Church a Temple of God. The materiall Temple vnder the Law was a figure of the ſpirituall vnder the Goſpell. The former was diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into three roomes; the Porch, the holy place, and the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> or Holy of holies. The Porch prefigured Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, which is the doore whereby we enter into the Church of Chriſt. The Holy place, the communion of the militant church vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly earth, ſeparated from the world. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of holies, whereinto the high Prieſt only entred, &amp; that once a yeare, preſignified the glorious kingdome of heauen, wherinto the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> entred once for all. There was one Court of the Temple common, whither acceſſe was denied to none: though they were vncleane or vncircumciſed, thus farre they might be admitted. There was another Court within that, allowed to none but the Iſraelites, &amp; of them to none but the cleane. There was a third, proper only to the Prieſts and Leuites, whither the Laitie might not come: thus farre they might bring their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, but further they might not offer to goe. In the Temple it ſelfe there was one roome, into which the Leuites might not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:521:22"/>enter, the Prieſts might. Another, whither the Prieſts might not come; but onely the high Prieſt, and euen hee but once yearely. Some paſſages of the Chriſtian Church are common to all, euen to the vncleane hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and foule-hearted ſinners. They haue acceſſe to Gods holy ordinances, and tread in his Courts; as the Phariſee came into the congregation, and <hi>Iudas</hi> receiued the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Other are ſecret and reſerued, wherein the faithfull onely conuerſe with God, and ſolace themſelues in the ſweet fruition of his gracious preſence.</p>
               <p>The materiall Temple in three diuiſions, ſeemed to be a cleare repreſentation of the Church in three degrees. The firſt ſignified the externall and viſible face of the Church, from which no profeſſor of Chriſt is debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The ſecond, the communion of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible Church vpon earth. The laſt, the higheſt heauen of Gods glorified Saints. Neither did thoſe roomes more exceed one another, then do theſe parts of the ſpirituall houſe of Chriſt. What are the moſt poliſhed corners of the Temple, to the ſpirituall &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtones of the Church? What be pebles to Saphirs, or marbles to Diamonds? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſome are more tranſported with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible monuments, then with liuing Saints. As it was a complaint long ſince, <hi>Fulget Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia in parietibus, luget in pauperibus.</hi> Yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:521:23"/>Temples are built for men, not men for Temples: and what is a glorious edifice, when the whole world is not worth one ſoule? Dead walls bee of ſmall value, to the liuing Temples of the holy Ghoſt: yea, the temple of our body, to the temple of Chriſts Body, his Church: yea the Temple of Gods Church militant on earth, to that which is triumphant in heauen. What is ſiluer and gold, Cedar and Marble, to thoſe diuine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, faith, truth, pietie, holineſſe? <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple did laſt but ſome 430. yeares, the Church is for eternitie. The Temple took vp but a little ſpace of ground, at moſt the Hill Sion, the Church is vniuerſally ſpread: in all parts of the world God hath his choſen.</p>
               <p>Did our intellectuall eyes truely behold the beauty of this Temple, wee would with that good Emperor, eſteeme it better to be a member of the Church, then head of the kingdome. We would ſet this one thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all worldly glories. As when <hi>Henry</hi> 4. that late <hi>Great</hi> king of France, was told of the king of Spaines ample dominions: as firſt he is king of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and I (quoth <hi>Henry</hi>) am king of France: he is king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and I am king of France: he is king of <hi>Portugall,</hi> and I am king of France: he is king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and I am king of France: he is king of the <hi>Sicilies,</hi> and I am king of France: hee is king of <hi>Noua Hiſpania,</hi> the Weſt Indies, and I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:521:23"/>am king of France: he thought the kingdome of France equiualent to all theſe. So let thy ſoule, O Chriſtian, ſolace it ſelfe againſt all the wants of thy mortall pilgrimage, in this, that thou art a member of the church. Another hath more wit or learning, yet I am a Chriſtian: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other hath more honour and preferment on earth, yet I am a Chriſtian: another hath more ſiluer and gold and riches, yet I am a Chriſtian: another hath large poſſeſſions, yet I haue an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in heauen, I am a Chriſtian. <hi>Dauid</hi> thought it not ſo happy to bee a King in his owne houſe, as to bee a doore-keeper in Gods houſe. Were our hearts throughly ſanctified, we would vnder-value all honours to this, that we are parts of this ſpirituall Temple, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Jdols.</head>
               <p>Euery deuice of man in the ſeruice of God is a meere Idol. Whatſoeuer we inuent out of Gods Schoole, or ſubſtitute in Gods roome, is to vs an Idol. Howſoeuer we flatter our ſelues, with reflecting all the honour on God, yet hee will reflect the vengeance on vs.
<note place="margin">Iob 13.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Shall a man ſpeake deceitfully for God,</hi> or tell a lye for his glory? Hee is not ſo penurious of meanes to honour himſelfe, as to be beholding to vs for a lye. The doctrine of vniuerſall grace ſeemes to make much for Gods glory, but himſelfe ſayes it is a lye; for <hi>he will haue mercie on whom he will haue
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:521:24"/>mercy, and whom hee will hee hardneth.</hi> To ſay that Chriſt in the wombe wrought many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, hath a faire ſhew of honouring him; but who can ſay it is not a lye? Sure, wee reade no ſuch matter. To diſtribute among the Saints departed ſeuerall Offices; as one to haue the charge of women in child-bed, another to bee the Patron of ſuch a Citie or Countrey; (to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their protection of beaſts, one for hogs, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for horſes) ſeemes to honour God in thus honouring them: but it is a lye, and a plaine derogation to his vniuerſall prouidence: yea as abſurd, as if the flies ſhould take vpon them to giue the charges and offices of this kingdome. To ſay, the Saints in heauen know the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of this nether world, and the condition of their ancient friends or children below, reading them in the Deitie, as by the reflection of a glaſſe; this is a fiction that carries a ſhew of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring God: but it doth indeed diſhonor him, by making creatures as omniſcient as their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. Beſides, how abſurd is it to ſay, that <hi>Iohn</hi> in <hi>Patmos</hi> ſeeing Chriſt, did ſee all that Chriſt ſaw. If I ſtanding on the ground, ſee a man on the top of a high Turret, doe I ſee all that hee ſeeth. If the ſight of him that looketh, bee to be meaſured by the ſight of him on whom hee looketh; it will follow that hee which looketh on a blinde man, ſhould ſee nothing at all. And who ſeeth not the blindnes of this conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?</p>
               <p>To ſay that all the worſhip done to the Virgin
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:521:24"/>mother, redounds to the honour of her Sonne and God, is a groſſe falſhood. The Idolatrous Iewes might as well haue pretended the honor of God, when they worſhipped the Queene of heauen. That fanaticall viſion of theirs,
<note place="margin">Specul. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empl.</note> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the two ladders that reached vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, while Chriſt was preparing to iudge the world: the one Red, at the top whereof Chriſt ſate: the other white, at the top whereof the Virgin ſate and when the Friers could not get vp the red ladder of Chriſt, but euermore tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled downe backward, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Francis</hi> called them vp the white ladder of our Lady, and there they were receiued. Did this make for the honour of Chriſt, when the red blood of our Sauiour is not ſo able to bring men to heauen, as the white milke of his mother? which muſt needs be the morall or meaning of it.
<note place="margin">Barrbad. in Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Euang.</note> Or the obſeruation of <hi>Barrhadius</hi> the Ieſuite, who made bold to aske Chriſt, why in his aſcenſion to heauen he did not take his mother along with him; and makes himſelfe this anſwer: It may be, Lord, for feare leſt thy heauenly Court ſhould bee in doubt, which of the two they ſhould goe firſt to meet, <hi>An tibi Domino ſuo, an ipſi Dominae ſuae,</hi> whether thee their Lord, or her their Lady: as if it had been well aduiſed of Chriſt to leaue his mother behind him, leſt ſhe ſhould ſhare part of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Did this make for the honour of Chriſt? To choke vp the knowledge of God, by preaching that Ignorance is the mother of Deuotion, hath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:521:25"/>ſmall colour of honouring God. The aſcribing of falſe miracles to the liuing or departed Saints, ſeemes to honour God, but ſure he will neuer thanke them for it. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being ſick, a blind man came to him, expecting that he could miraculouſly reſtore his ſight: but that good Father ſent him away with a check, <hi>Doeſt thou think that if I could cure thee by miracle, that I would not by miracle cure my ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a fooliſh thought, that God will bee glorified by a lie. Our iudiciall Aſtrologers, that tye mens deſtinies to the Starres and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, pretend Gods honour, who hath giuen ſuch vertue and influence to his creatures; but indeed make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no better then Idols. Though the Sunne and Moone bee good and neceſſary, yet to adore the Sunne and Moone is flat Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. It was not <hi>Mercury</hi> that made the theefe, nor <hi>Venus</hi> that made the ſtrumpet: as when the husband cudgeld his adulterous wife, and ſhee complained that he was vnnaturall to ſtrike his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wne fleſh; alledging that it was not <hi>ſhee</hi> that playd the harlot, but <hi>Venus</hi> in her: to whom he replied, that neither was it <hi>ſhee</hi> that he did beat, but <hi>Venus</hi> in her, or rather <hi>Venus</hi> out of her.</p>
               <p>To make this vſefull to our ſelues; let vs take heed of fancying an other ſeruice of God, then hee hath preſcribed vs. Euery Maſter in his owne family, appoints the manner how he will be ſerued. He that requires our ſeruice, requires it his owne way; or elſe he holds vs to ſerue our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:521:25"/>ſelues, not him. Shall we make our ſelues wiſer then our Maker, as if he did not beſt know what would beſt pleaſe him? Shall heauen giue a bleſſing to that, which was deuiſed againſt the will of heauen? Doth not God threaten them with the addition of plagues, that ſhall adde to his precepts? If ſuch deuices be good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, why did not God command them? Did he want wiſdome? If they bee not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, why doe wee vſe them? Is it not our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous folly? The Lords Ielouſie is ſtirred vp by the rivalitie, not onely of a falſe God, but of a falſe worſhip. Nothing is more dangerous, then to mint his ſeruices in our owne braines. <hi>In vaine doe they worſhip mee, teaching for doctrines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 16.9.</note> 
                  <hi>the commandements of men.</hi> Is it not grieuous for men to loſe all their labour, and that in the maine buſines of their life? That ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred oblations, ſo many thouſand prayers, ſo much coſt of their purſes, ſo much affliction to their bodies, ſo much anguiſh of their ſoules, ſhould be all forceles, fruitles? Like a dog that hunts counter, and takes great paines to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>Euill deeds may haue ſometimes good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; but thoſe good meanings are anſwered with euill recompences. Many beſtow their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, their goods, their bloods, and yet receiue torments in ſtead of thanks. When the Apoſtle bids vs <hi>mortifie our earthly members,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.5.</note> hee does not intend violence to our ſelues, but to our ſinnes.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:521:26"/>There is one mortification, to caſt our ſelues out of the world: there is another mortification, to caſt the world out of vs. A body macerated with ſcourges, diſabled with faſtings, wearied with pilgrimages; was none of S. <hi>Pauls mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Who hath required this at your hands?</hi> Where is no commaund impoſed, no reward propoſed; no promiſe made, if you doe; no puniſhment threatned, if you doe not; what fruit can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected but ſhame? Muſt wee needs either doe nothing, or that which is worſe then nothing? Shall we offer ſo much, ſuffer ſo much, and all in vaine? <hi>Quis haec à vobis?</hi> Let him pay you your wages, that did ſet you on worke. Neuer plead your owne reaſon, where God hath ſet a plaine interdiction. He that ſuffers his faith to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by his reaſon, may haue a fat reaſon, but a leane faith. That man is not worthy to bee a follower of Chriſt, who hath not denied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; therefore denied his Reaſon; for his reaſon is no ſmall piece of himſelfe. If Reaſon get the head in this diuine buſineſſe, it preſently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes with will, and will commands the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo this new Triumvirate ſhall gouerne the Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Saboll par.</hi> 1.</note> not Faith. But as when three Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors were ſent from Rome, to appeaſe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betweene <hi>Nicomedes</hi> and <hi>Pruſias;</hi> whereof one was troubled with a Megrim in his head, another had the Gowt in his toes, and the third was a foole; <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid merrily, that Ambaſſage had neither <hi>Head,</hi> nor <hi>Foot,</hi> nor <hi>Heart.</hi> So that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:521:26"/>man ſhall neither haue a head to conceiue the truth, nor a foot to walke in the wayes of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, nor a heart to receiue the comforts of ſaluation; that ſuffers his reaſon, will, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to vſurpe vpon his faith.</p>
               <p>Hence it comes to paſſe, that the moſt horrid ſinnes are turned into Idols; by ſetting our owne reaſons againſt the manifeſt will of God. Thus lies ſhall bee father'd vpon the <hi>Father of truth,</hi> and truth vpon the <hi>Father of lies.</hi> Thus breach of faith, and periurie, ſhall be held Orthodoxe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions. Yea, that execrable monſter, whereof this day remembers vs, Treaſon it ſelfe, ſhall be held good Doctrine. <hi>Rude cacodaemon,</hi> that ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke Idol, that groſſe deuill ſhall be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Si fas cadendo coeleſtia ſcandere,</hi> If this be the way to the kingdome of heauen, if thus men may merit to be ſtarres in the Firmament, by embruing their hands in the bloud-Royall of Princes; what Ieſuite will not be a Star? When ſuch bee their principles, ſuch muſt needes bee their practices. What though God condemne Treaſon to hell, when the Pope will aduance it to heauen? What though the Diuine Scripture doth ranke traitors among dogs &amp; deuils, when the Pope will number them among Saints? It was wont to be ſaid, <hi>Ex quolibet ligno non fit Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius,</hi> euery block is not fit to make an Image. Yet now, the moſt monſtrous ſinne that euer the deuill ſhaped in his Infernall forge, is not onely by the practice, but euen by the Doctrine of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:521:27"/>Rome, turned into an Idol. What is that we ſhal call fin, when murther &amp; Treaſon is held religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Alas for our age, to beare the date of theſe impieties! That our poſterity ſhould euer reade in our Chronicles: In ſuch a yeare in ſuch a day Traitors conſpired againſt their lawfull &amp; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne: and that in thoſe dayes there was a ſect of men liuing, that did labour in volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous writings, to iuſtifie thoſe horrible facts. But oh, may thoſe peſtiferous monuments be as faſt deuoured by obliuion, as the authors and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors themſelues are ſwallowed vp by confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And the ſame God deliuer vs his people from their conſpiracies, that hath deliuered this his Church from their Idolatries.</p>
               <p>Thus wee haue looked abroad, but now haue we no Idols at home? O how happy was it, if they were as farre from the Temple, as they are from agreement with the Temple? I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in this diſcouery; there be three maine Idols among vs; Vaine Preaſure, vaine Honor, and Riches: &amp; it is to be feared, that theſe three vanities haue more clients then the Trinity that made vs. The firſt is an Idol of the water, the next an Idol of the ayre, the laſt an Idol of the earth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Vaine <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> and oh what a world of fooliſh worſhippers flocke to this merry God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe! Shee hath a Temple in euery corner: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie ſits in Tauernes, burning ſmoky Incenſe, and ſacrificing drink-offrings to her. So that if a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:521:27"/>man ſhould <hi>propheſie of wine and ſtrong drinke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 2.11.</note> he were a Prophet fit for this age: but to preach ſobrietie, is held but a dry doctrine. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend wine for the excellency of it; but if it could ſpeak, as it can take away ſpeech, it would complaine, that by our abuſe, both the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are loſt: for the excellent man doth ſo ſpoile the excellent wine, vntill the excellent wine hath ſpoiled the excellent man. O that a man ſhould take pleaſure in that which makes him no man: that he ſhould let a thiefe in at his mouth, to ſteale away his wit: that for a little throat-indulgence, hee ſhould kill in himſelfe both the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> his reaſon; but euen the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi> his regeneration, &amp; ſo commit two murders at once! In euery Brothell this Idol hath her temple; where the bed of vncleannes is the Altar, the Prieſt a ſtrumpet, and the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, a burning fleſh offred to <hi>Moloch.</hi> It is no rare thing for a man to make an Idol of his Miſtres, and to ſpend more time in her courtings, then he doth at his prayers; more coſt on her body, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon his own ſoule. Images were but dead Idols, but painted Popinjayes be liuing Idols <hi>Pleaſure</hi> hath a larger extent, then I can now ſtand to ſuruey: this may be called an Idol of the <hi>Water;</hi> fluid and vnſatisfying.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Vaine <hi>Honour</hi> is the Idol of fooles: no wiſe man euer ſought felicity in ſhadows. His Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is Pride, his Altar Ambition, his Seruice Flattery, his Sacrifice Petulancy. Silly <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:521:28"/>to make an Idol of a <hi>Chariot:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 37.24. Ezek 28.4.</note> and no wiſer <hi>Prince of Tyre,</hi> to make an Idol of his <hi>own brain!</hi> Men miſtake the way to bee great, while they neglect the way to be good. All the while a man hunts after his ſhadow, hee miſ-ſpends his time and paines: for the Sun is vpon his back, behind him, and his ſhadow is ſtill vn-ouertaken before him: but let him turne his face to the Sun, &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that, his ſhadow ſhall follow him. In vaine doth that man purſue honor, his ſhadow, while he turnes his face from vertue and goodnes; he ſhall miſſe what hee ſo labors to catch: but let him ſet his face toward Chriſt, the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and run to the high prize of eternitie, this ſhadow ſhall wayt vpon him; for <hi>thoſe that honour me, I will honour,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God reſiſteth the proud;</hi> and good reaſon, for the proud reſiſteth God. Other ſins diuert a man from God, only Pride brings him againſt God, &amp; brings God againſt him. There is nothing in this world worth our pride, but that moſſe will grow to a ſtone. <hi>Pride</hi> is euer dangerous, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt when it puffes vs vp with a preſumption of merit. Thus the Romiſts preſume to do more good works, and thoſe more perfect then God requires: ſo that he is become a debter to them, &amp; bound to make them ſatisfaction. But doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, God wil more eaſily beare with thoſe ſinnes wherof we repent, then with that righteouſnes whereof we preſume.
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>I am not as other men are,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Phariſee;</hi> &amp; the clock of his tongue went truer then the dyall of his heart; he was not like
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:521:28"/>other men indeed, ſure he was like none of them that ſhould be ſaued. Humility is ſo hard a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to get into the heart, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was faine to come downe from heauen, in his owne perſon to teach it.</p>
               <p>Pride is euen conuerſant about good workes and graces; this <hi>Saul</hi> loues to be among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. So that if a man haue ſome good meaſure of ſanctification, and of aſſurance of eternall life; it will be hard not to be proud of that. Pride hath hurt many, Humility neuer yet did harme. A man goes in at a dore, and he ſtoops: the dore is high enough, yet he ſtoops: you will ſay, he needs not ſtoope; yea, but ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern.</note> there is no hurt in his ſtooping: otherwiſe he may catch a knocke, this way he is ſafe. A man may beare himſelfe too high vpon the fauor of God, there is no danger in his ſtooping, no harme in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Let me rather be the loweſt of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, then the nobleſt among his enemies. The honour of this world is at beſt but a golden dreame, from which men commonly awake in contempt. This is an Idol of the <hi>Ayre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. Wealth</hi> is the couetous mans Idol; <hi>Iob</hi> ſhewes the form of his Canonization: <hi>He makes gold his hope, and ſayes to the wedge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 31.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art my confidence.</hi> As treaſon ſets vp a new king, for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Abſolon:</hi> ſo couetouſnes ſets vp a new god, for <hi>Iehouah, Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon.</hi> But, O miſerable god, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> that cannot defend it ſelfe from ruſting or robbing. And, O more miſerable man, that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:521:29"/>truſts himſelfe vpon the keeping of that god, which himſelfe is faine to keepe.
<note place="margin">Iudg. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Micah</hi> did not worſhip his ſiluer, till it was caſt into the forme of an Idol: theſe ſpare the labour of forming, and worſhip the very metall. The Superſtitious adore <hi>Aurum in Idolo,</hi> gold in the Idol: the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous find <hi>Idolum in Auro,</hi> an Idol in the very gold. <hi>Metalla</hi> ſeemes to ſound <hi>quaſi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Poſt alia neceſſaria:</hi> when they had manured the ground, ſowen ſeeds, gathered fruits, and found out other things to ſuſtaine life, then <hi>Itum eſt in viſcera terrae,</hi> they digged into the bowels of the earth. O that man ſhould lay that next his heart, which God hath placed vnder his feet! that the thing which might bee beſt ſpared, ſhould bee moſt admired! <hi>Mammon</hi> hath his Temple, the world: God hath his Temple, the Church: but there be many that balke Gods Temple to goe to <hi>Mammons:</hi> and they offer faire, that make ſome reuerence to God, as they paſſe by him to the world. Hence it is, that ſo many get riches, and ſo few godlines. The Poets faine <hi>Pluto</hi> to be the god of Hell, &amp; the god of Riches; (as if Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Hell had both one Maſter.) Sometime they ſet him forth lame and ſlow-paced, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time nimble as fire. When <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſends him to a Souldier or a Scholer, he goes limping: when hee ſends him to on of his Pandars, he flies like lightning. The morall is, the wealth that comes in Gods name, comes ſlowly, and with diligent labour: but that which is haled in with an euill
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:521:29"/>conſcience, is both haſty &amp; abundant in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. This is the worldlings maine god, all the reſt be ſubordinate to him. <hi>Si modo Iupiter mihi propitius ſit, minores deos flocci facio:</hi> So long as <hi>Mammon</hi> fauours them, or their <hi>Great Diana</hi> multiplies their gaines; they ſcorne the other petty gods, making account with a little money to buy them all. This is an Idol of the <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>No agreement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye cannot ſerue God and Mammon;</hi> you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for it, you ſhall neuer compound it. <hi>Gehezi</hi> cannot run after the forbidden talents, but hee muſt leaue his maſter. Some indeed here, haue ſo finely diſtinguiſhed of the buſines, that though they ſerue God, they wil ſerue him more thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and pleaſe him as good cheape as they can. They haue reſolued not to do euill, though they may gaine by it: yet for gaine, they will venture as neere euill, as poſſibly they can and miſſe it. But when it comes to puſh, it wil be found, that for one ſcruple of gold, they will make no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of conſcience. But as thoſe Inhabitants of <hi>Iudea,</hi> that ſerued both God &amp; Idols, did indeed neither ſerue God nor Idols: ſo theſe higlers, while they would haue two maſters, haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed neuer a one. For in the euill day, their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the world will renounce them, &amp; then their maſter Chriſt will not receiue them: ſo highly doth hee ſcorne ſuch a competition. Man was made to ſerue God, and the world to ſerue man: ſo the world at beſt is but Gods ſeruants ſeruant. Now if we plead our ſelues Gods ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, what an indign &amp; prepoſterous thing is it, to take our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:521:30"/>owne ſeruant, and make him competitor with our Maſter? <hi>God</hi> ſayes, lend, giue, clothe, feed, harbor: <hi>Mammon</hi> ſayes, Take, gather, extort, oppreſſe, ſpoile: whether of theſe is our God? Euen he that is moſt obeyed. No leſſe might be ſaid for pleaſures and honors, or whatſoeuer is delectable to fleſh and blood. <hi>The loue of this world is enmity to God;</hi> and the Eaſt &amp; Weſt ſhall ſooner vnite their forces, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled.</p>
               <p>It is the Deuils eſpeciall ayme, to bring theſe Idols neere the Temple: he finds no ſuch plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to dominere in his owne hell; but he hath a mind to Paradiſe: One wittily obſerueth, that Chriſt choſe poore Fiſhermen, as the fitteſt to receiue his Oracles, &amp; to plant his Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Satan ſcorned to looke ſo low, as to tempt them. He ſtudied to preuent Chriſt among the Kings of the earth, and great Doctors, neuer ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting ſilly fiſhers. But when he found himſelf deceiued, he will then make their whole profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to fare the worſe for it; he beares the whole ſucceſſion of their Tribe an old grudge. Before, he paſſed by them, and tempted the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; now he wil ſooner tempt them then Kings and Emperors.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.12</note> The Church doth <hi>not iudge them that are without,</hi> but them <hi>within:</hi> and Satan had rather foile one within, then a hundred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. Hee hath a deſire to all, but eſpecially he loues a religious ſoule: he would eat that with more greedines, then <hi>Rachel</hi> did her Mandrakes. The fall of one Chriſtian better pleaſeth him, then of many vnbeleeuers. No King makes war againſt his owne loyall ſubiects, but againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:521:30"/>&amp; enemies. The deuill is to ſubtill, to ſpend his malice vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that do him ready ſeruice He cares not ſo much to multiply Idols in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> as to get one into <hi>Sion.</hi> To maintaine prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> in the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at the table of <hi>Ieſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> as it were vnder Gods noſe: or to ſet vp <hi>Calues</hi> at <hi>Bethel,</hi> in ſcorne of the Temple; this is his ambition. The Fox ſeldome preyes neere home, nor doth Satan meddle with his owne; they are as ſure as temptation can make them. What Iailor laies more chaines vpon the ſhack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led malefactor, that loues his priſon, and would not change? The Pirate ſpends not a ſhot vpon a cole-ſhip; but he lets flie at the rich Merchant. <hi>Cantabit vacuus,</hi> the empty traueller may paſſe vnmoleſted: it is the full barne that inuites the thiefe. If we were not belonging to the Temple, we ſhould not be aſſaulted with ſo many Idols; if not Chriſtians, fewer tentations.</p>
               <p>Now the more potent and malicious our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, the more reſolute and ſtrong bee our reſiſtance. The more extreame the cold is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, the more doth the naturall heat fortifie it ſelfe within, &amp; guard the heart. It is the note of the vngodly, that they <hi>bleſſe Idols:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 66.3.</note> if we would not bee ſuch, let vs bleſſe our ſelues from Idols. And as wee haue baniſhed the materiall Idols out of our Temples, ſo let vs driue theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ones out of our hearts Let vs ſay with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> we haue heard God, &amp; ſeene him;
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.8.</note> 
                  <hi>What haue we to doe any more with Idols?</hi> The vices of the religious are the ſhame of religion: the ſight of this hath made the ſtouteſt Champions of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:521:31"/>Chriſt melt into teares.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.136</note> 
                  <hi>Riuers of waters run down mine eyes, becauſe they keep not thy law. Dauid</hi> was one of thoſe great Worthies of the world, not matchable in his times; yet he weepes. Did hee teare in pieces a beare like a kid? reſcue a lambe with the death of a lyon? foile a mighty gyant, that had dared the whole army of God? Did he like a whirlewind, beare and beat down his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies before him; and now does he, like a childe or a woman, fall a weeping? Yes, he had heard the name of God blaſphemed, ſeene his holy rites prophaned, his ſtatutes vilipended, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered to the pure and intemerate Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of that holy virgin, Religion: this reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that valiant heart into teares;
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters run down mine eyes.</hi> So <hi>Paul, I tell you of them weeping, that are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt.</hi> Had he with ſo magnanimous a courage, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtripes and perſecutions, run through perils of all ſorts and ſizes, fought with beaſts at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> been rapt vp to heauen, and learn'd his Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie among the Angels; &amp; does he now weep? Yes, he had ſeene Idols in the Temple, Impiety in the Church of God: this made that great ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit melt into teares. If we ſee theſe Idols in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or feele them in our ſelues, and complaine not; we giue God and the Church iuſt cauſe to complaine of vs. Now the Lord deliuer his Temples from theſe Idols.</p>
               <p>But all this while wee haue walked in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; and you will ſay, <hi>Quod omnibus dicitur, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini dicitur:</hi> let mee now therefore come to particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:521:31"/>
               <head>The Temple of God</head>
               <p>Is euery <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> as the Church is his great Temple, ſo his little temple is euery man. We are not onely through his grace, liuing ſtones in his Temple, but liuing temples in his <hi>Sion:</hi> each one bearing about him a little ſhrine of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Maieſtie. Whereſoeuer God dwels, there is his Temple: therefore the beleeuing heart is his Temple, for there he dwels. As wee poore creatures of the earth haue our being in him, ſo he the God of heauen hath his dwelling in vs. It is true, that the heauen of heauens is not able to containe him; yet the narrow lodgings of our renewed ſoules are take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp for him. What were a houſe made with hands vnto the God of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; vnleſſe there bee a ſpirit for him to dwell in made without hands? Here if the Body be the Temple, the Soule is Prieſt: if that be not the offerer, the Sacrifice will not be accepted.</p>
               <p>In this Spirituall Temple, firſt there is the <hi>Porch;</hi> which we may conceiue to be the <hi>Mouth,</hi> Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> prayes to haue a <hi>Watch ſet at the doore of his lips,</hi> to ward the gate of Gods Temple. This may ſeeme to be one reaſon of <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting</hi> in former times <hi>by a kiſſe;</hi> they did kiſſe the gate of Gods Temple. Here the <hi>Feare</hi> of God is the <hi>Porter;</hi> who is both ready to let in his friends, and reſolute to keepe out his enemies. Let him ſpecially watch for two ſorts of foes, the one, a traitor that goes out, euill ſpeaking: the other, a thiefe that ſteales in, too much drinking.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Holy place</hi> is the ſanctified mind, that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals the <hi>Inner man.</hi> Herebe thoſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:521:32"/>riches and ornaments, the diuine graces. Here not onely Iuſtice, and Faith, and Temperance, ſing their parts, but the whole Quire of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vertues make vp the harmony.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Holy of holies</hi> is the purified Conſcience, wherin ſtand the Cherubins, Faith &amp; Loue; and the Mercy-ſeat, ſhaded with the wings of thoſe glorious Angels: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which Propitiatory God giues the gracious teſtimonies of his good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>witneſsing with our ſpirits that we are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> In this Sacrary doth the Lord conuerſe with the ſoule; takes her hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble confeſſion, giues her ſweet abſolution. It is a place whither nor man nor Angell can enter; only the high Prieſt <hi>Ieſus</hi> comes, not once a yeare, but daily; and communicates ſuch ineſtimable fauours and comforts, as no tongue can expreſſe.</p>
               <p>Here we find the <hi>Arke,</hi> wherein the Royall law, and Pot of heauenly Manna are preſerued. the one reſtraining vs from ſinne to come by a happy preuention, the other aſſuring vs pardon of ſinne paſt with a bleſſed conſolation. Let vs looke further vpon the <hi>golden Candleſticks,</hi> our illumined vnderſtandings; wherby we perceiue the will of our Maker, and diſcerne the way of our eternall peace. Then vpon the <hi>Tables of Shew-bread,</hi> which be our holy memories, that keepe the bread of life continually ready with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs. Yea, Memory is the treaſury of this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which ſo lockes vp thoſe celeſtiall riches, that wee can draw them forth for vſe at all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. Here is alſo the <hi>Vaile,</hi> and thoſe ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken curtaines, and coſtly hangings; the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:521:32"/>of Chriſt, which makes vs acceptable to God; both hiding our own infirmities, and dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs with his vertues. Here is the <hi>Altar</hi> for ſacrifice, the contrite heart: the beaſt to be ſlain is not found among our heards, but among our affections; we muſt ſacrifice our luſts: the knife to kill them, which would elſe kill vs, is the Sword of the Spirit, the Word of God: the fire to conſume them is holy zeale, kindled in our breſts by the inſpiration of God.</p>
               <p>There be other ſacrifices alſo for vs to offer in this Temple, on this Altar. Beſides our praiſes and prayers;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note> the <hi>ſetting forth of our prayer as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and the lifting vp our hands as an euening ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice:</hi> there is mercy, &amp; charitable deeds. What is deuotion without compaſſion? What, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice without mercy?
<note place="margin">Math. 5.23</note> 
                  <hi>If thy brother hath ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee,</hi> yea, if thou haue ought that ſhould haue bin thy brothers; thy oblation will ſtink in Gods noſtrils. It was an old complaint of the Church, that her ſtones were clothed, and her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naked; that the curious found matter to delight them, but the diſtreſſed found not bread to ſuſtaine them. Therfore ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſa.</hi> 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Si habes taurum pinguem, occide pauperibus:</hi> If thou haue a fat Bull, ſacrifice it to the poore. Though they cannot drink the blood of goats, they can eat the fleſh of bulls. And he that ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.12.</note> 
                  <hi>If I were hungry, I would not tell thee;</hi> yet wil acknowledge at the laſt day, <hi>I was hungry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>and thou didſt feed mee; Come thou bleſſed.</hi> The poore haue Gods commendatory letters to vs, and our prayers be our commendatory letters to God: if we will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:521:33"/>not hearken to him, how ſhould he gratifie vs? Thus, O Chriſtian, art thou a mouing Temple of the liuing God.</p>
               <p>Let this teach vs all to adorne theſe Temples with decent graces. Superſtition cares not what it beſtowes on materiall Fanes: mountainous Columnes, Marble Pillars, gorgeous Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which yet are not ſenſible of their owne ornaments; ſpangled Crucifixes, Images clad in Silkes and Tiſſues, with embroydered Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, and Tables beſet with Pearles and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds. Thus bountifull is ſhe to her ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Oh that our Religion would doe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for theſe ancient and ruinous walls. But how much more precious bee theſe ſpirituall Temples of our ſelues? How much more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ought to be their furnitures?</p>
               <p>Firſt then, if we be the Temples of God, let vs bee holy: for <hi>holineſſe, O Lord, becommeth thy Houſe for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is <hi>Domus orationis;</hi> they muſt haue the continuall exerciſes of Prayer. <hi>In Templo vis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare? In te ora.</hi> Wouldſt thou pray in Gods Temple? Pray in thy ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſound of the high praiſes of God muſt bee heard in theſe Temples: <hi>There euery man ſpeaks of his honour.</hi> It pleaſeth the Lord to <hi>inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the praiſes of Iſrael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.9.</note> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. <hi>Wee haue thought of thy louing kindnes, O God, in the midſt of thy Temple:</hi> that is, euen in the midſt of our ſelues, in our owne hearts. There let vs think vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his mercies, there eccho forth his praiſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Inhabitant diſpoſeth all the roomes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:521:33"/>of his houſe: if God dwell in vs, let him rule vs. Submit thy will to his word, thy affections to his Spirit. It is fit that euery man ſhould beare rule in his owne houſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let vs bee glad when hee is in vs, and giue him no diſturbance. Let not the foulenes of any roome make him diſlike his habitation. Cleanſe all the ſluttiſh corners of ſinne, and perfume the whole houſe with <hi>Myrrhe</hi> &amp; <hi>Caſsia.</hi> Still be get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting neerer to thy Land-lord: other Inhabitants come home to their houſes; but here the houſe muſt ſtriue to come home to the Inhabitant. Whenſoeuer God comestoward thee, meet him by the way, and bid him welcome to his owne.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Laſtly, if we be the Lords houſes, then no bodies elſe. The materiall Temples are not to bee diuerted to common offices: much more ſhould the ſpirituall be vſed only for Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Let vs not alienate his rights: thus hee will ſay, <hi>This is my houſe, heere will I dwell, for I haue a delight therein.</hi> O may we ſo adorne theſe Temples with graces, that God may take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Idols.</head>
               <p>Theſe be the Temples: the Idols that haunt them, wee better know, then know how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: they bee our luſtes, and inordinate affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; the rebellions of our corrupt nature, which <hi>fight against the Soule,</hi> defile the bodie, and diſgrace the Temples of Gods Spirit. So I paſſe from them, to the laſt poynt; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe libidinous Idols, and thoſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Temples, there can be</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:521:34"/>
               <head>No agreement.</head>
               <p>God wil dwel with no Inmates: if vncleannes be there,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.27</note> will the fountain of all purity abide it? Will Chriſt dwell with an adulterer? He that will ſuffer no vncleane thing to enter his citie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, will he himſelfe dwell in an vncleane citie below? O think how execrable that ſin is, which doth not onely take the members of Chriſt, and makes them the limbs of an harlot; but euen tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Chriſts Temples into ſtinking Brothels. Our hearts bee the Altars to ſend vp the ſweet Incenſe of deuout prayers and cherefull thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings; if the ſmoke of malicious thoughts bee found there, will God accept our oblations? Is it poſſible, that man ſhould pleaſe his Father, that will not be reconciled to his brother? The Lamps of knowledge and ſobrietie are burning within vs; will not the deluge of drink put them out? Will the Lord dwell in a drunken body? Muſt we not ceaſe to be his Temples, when we become <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Tuns and tunnels? There is <hi>Manna,</hi> the bread of life within vs; will not Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſme &amp; throat-indulgence corrupt it? There is peace in vs, will not pride and contention af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright it? There is the loue of heauen in vs, wil not the loue of the world baniſh it? Shall the graces of God cohabitate with the vices of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan? Wil the Temple of God indure Idols? No, theſe Eagles plumes wil not brook the blending with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fethers: this heauenly gold ſcornes the mixture of baſe and ſophiſticate metalls.</p>
               <p>Let vs ſearch our hearts, &amp; ranſake them nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly: if we doe not caſt out theſe Idols, God
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:521:34"/>will not own vs for his Temples.
<note place="margin">Math. 21.13</note> 
                  <hi>My Houſe ſhall bee called the houſe of prayer:</hi> this was Gods <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation: But you haue made it a den of theeues:</hi> this is mans <hi>Impropriation.</hi> Let vs take heed of impropriating Gods houſe; remembring howhe hath reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged ſuch a profanation with ſcourges. <hi>Wee are bought with a price,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20</note> 
                  <hi>therefore let vs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God both in body &amp; ſpirit, for they are his:</hi> His purchaſe, his Temple, his inheritance, his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: do not loſe ſo gracious an owner, by the moſt vngracious ſacriledge. You ſee many rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned houſes, which haue bin once kings palaces: learne by thoſe dead ſpectacles to keepe your ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like fortunes: leſt God ſay of you, <hi>Hoc Templum meum fuit,</hi> this was my houſe; but now becauſe it took in Idols, I haue forſaken it.</p>
               <p>Or what if wee doe not ſet vp Idols in theſe Temples, when we make the Temples themſelues Idols? or ſay not with <hi>Iſrael, Make vs gods,</hi> while we make gods of our ſelues? while we dreſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and erect ſhrines to our own braines, &amp; kiſſe our own hands for the good they haue done vs? If we attribute ſomething to our ſelues, how is <hi>Chriſt al in all</hi> with vs? Do we iuſtly blame them that worſhip the <hi>Beaſt</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet find out a new Idolatry at home? Shal we refuſe to adore the Saints &amp; Angels, and yet giue diuine worſhip to our ſelues, duſt and aſhes? If victory crowne our battels, if plenty fill our garners, or ſucceſſe anſwere our endeuours; muſt the glory of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect vpon our own atchieuements? This is a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vality that God will not endure, to make ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Temples nothing but Idols. But as the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:521:35"/>Iuſtice ſaid of the ill-ſhap'd Rood, thogh it be not well fauoured enough for a god, it will ſerue to make an excellent deuill. So proud duſt and aſhes, that arrogates the honor of God, and impropriates it to himſelfe; though he be too foule for a Temple, yet he is fit enough for an Idol. When <hi>Dauid</hi> prayes, <hi>Libera me ab homine malo, Deliuer me from the euill man, O Lord.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> after much ſtudy and ſcrutiny to find out this euill man, at laſt lights vpon him; <hi>ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine malo,</hi> that is, <hi>à me ipſo: Deliuer me from the euill man,</hi> deliuer me from <hi>my ſelfe;</hi> Deliuer <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> from <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> I am that <hi>euill</hi> man. So, of all Idolatries, God deliuer vs from a ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious worſhip of our ſelues. Some haue Idolized their Princes, ſome their Miſtreſſes, ſome their Manufactures; but they are innumerable that haue Idolized themſelues. He is a rare man that hath no Idol, no little god in a boxe, no eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſinne in his heart, to which he giues vxori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and affectionate Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The only way to mend all, is for euery man to begin with himſelf. In vain ſhall we blame thoſe faults abroad, which we tolerate at home. That man makes himſelf ridiculous, who leauing his own houſe on fire, runs to quench his neigbors Let but euery man pull a brand from this fire, the flame will go out alone: if euery ſoule clenſe his owne Temple, all ſhall be quit of Idols, and God wil accept of all. A multitude is but a heap of vnities; the more we take away, the fewer we leaue behind. When a field is ouergrowne with weeds, the beſt courſe to haue a good generall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:521:35"/>harueſt, is for euery man to weed his owne ground. When we would haue the ſtreet cleanſed, let euery man ſweep his owne doore, and it is quickly done. But while euery man cenſures, &amp; none amends, we do but talk againſt Idols, with ſtill vnclenſed Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples.</p>
               <p>Let vs pray for vniuerſall repentance, like a good <hi>Ioſias,</hi> to purge the houſes of God: till luſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, pride and couetouſneſſe, fraud and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, malice and drunkennes, be no more found among vs: till euery thing be caſt out, and nothing let in, that is vncleane. So ſhall the Lord dwell in vs with content, and we ſhall dwell in him with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Here we ſhall be a Temple for Him, hereafter he ſhall be a Temple for vs. So we find that glorious Citie deſcribed, <hi>I ſaw no Temple therein,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>but the Lord God Almightie, and the Lambe was the Temple of it.</hi> Wee are Gods Temple on earth, God ſhall bee our Temple in heauen. To this purpoſe, the Spirit of God ſanctifie vs, and bee for euer ſanctified in vs. Amen.</p>
               <p>Some may haply (long ere this) haue preiudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their cenſures; How is this <hi>Opus diei in die ſuo?</hi> What is all this to the buſineſſe of the day? I might haue preuented the obiection, by comparing Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie with Treaſon: the one being a breach of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the Lord, the other a breach of allegiance to the Lords Annointed. Idolatry is a Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and Treaſon is a kind of Idolatry againſt the King. From both which the diuine grace, and our holy obedience deliuer vs all. I conclude with application to the Time.</p>
               <p>This is one of thoſe bleſſed dayes celebrated for the deliuerance of our gracious Soueraigne: and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:521:36"/>well may the deliuerance of a King, of ſuch a King, deſerue a day of gratulation. When God deliuers a priuate man, he doth, as it were, repeat his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but the deliuerance of a King, is alwayes a choyce piece in the Lords Chronicle. The Story, how he was endangered, and how preſerued, this place hath diuers times witneſſed; and that in a more punctuall manner, then I haue either ſtrength, or art, or time to match. A hard time it ſeemed to be, when a King was impriſoned, when he had no guard with him but his Innocency, no ſubiect but a Traytor. But there was a ſtronger with him, then all they could be againſt him. A good Prince hath more guards then one: he hath, 1. a ſubſidiary guard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of mortall men. 2. An inward guard, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie of his owne Conſcience. 3. A ſpirituall guard, the prayers of his faithfull ſubiects. 4. A ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial guard, the protection of diligent &amp; powerfull Angels. 5. A diuine guard, his Makers prouidence that fenceth him in with a wall of fire, which ſhall at once both preſerue him, and conſume his enemies.</p>
               <p>But my purpoſe is not to bring your thoughts back to the view of his perill, but to ſtir your hearts vp to thankfulneſſe for his preſeruation. He is iuſtly ſtyled, <hi>The Defender of the Faith:</hi> he hath euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Faith, and the Faith hath euer defended him. Hee hath preſerued the Temple of God from Idols, and therefore God hath preſerued him from all his enemies. Surely that Prouidence, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him from thoſe early Conſpiracies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath been aſſaulted from his cradle, meant him for ſome extraordinary benefit, and matchleſſe good to the Chriſtian world. Hee that gaue him
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:521:36"/>both life and Crowne (almoſt) together, hath ſtill miraculouſly preſerued them both, from all the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging violences of Rome and Hell. Now when the Lord deliuered him, what did he elſe but euen deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs all? That we might reioyce in his ſafety, as the Romans did in the recouery of <hi>Germanicus;</hi> when they ran with lampes and ſacrifices to the Capitoll, and there ſung with ſhouts and acclamations; <hi>Salua Roma, ſalua Patria, ſaluus Germanicus:</hi> the Citie is ſafe, the Country is ſafe, and all in the ſafetie of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus.</hi> While we conſider the bleſſings which we enioy by his gracious Gouernment; that the eſtates we haue gotten with honeſt induſtry, may be ſafely conueyed to our poſterity: that we ſit vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of peace, and may teach our children to know the Lord: that the good man may build vp Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Hoſpitals, without trembling to thinke of ſauage and barbarous violences to pull them down: that our Deuotions be not moleſted with vproares, nor men called from their callings by mutinies: that our Temples be not profaned with Idols, nor the Seruice of God blended with ſuperſtitious deuices: that our temporall eſtate is preſerued in liberty, our ſpirituall eſtate may bee improued in pietie, and our eternall eſtate aſſured vs in glory: that our liues be protected, and in quiet our ſoules may be ſaued: for ſuch a King of men, bleſſe we the God of Kings; and ſing for his deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as they did for their <hi>Germani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> as priuatly euery day, ſo this day in our publike Aſſemblies; <hi>Salua Britannia, Salua Eccleſia, ſaluus</hi> IACOBVS: Our Kingdome is ſafe, the Church of God is ſafe, our whole Eſtate is ſafe, wee are all ſafe and happie, in the ſafetie and happineſſe of King
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:521:37"/>IAMES. O that as we haue good cauſe to emulate, ſo alſo we would truly imitate the gratulation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> we for our King that hath preſerued the Temple,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 5.12.13.</note> as they for their King that built the Temple; while the Leuites and ſingers ſtood with Harps and Cymbals and Viols, and the Prieſts blowing with Trumpets; as if they had all been one man, and made one ſweet harmony to the praiſe of God.</p>
               <p>For theſe publike &amp; extraordinary bleſſings, God requires publike and extraordinary praiſes: that this great Aſſembly with prepared hearts, and religious affections, ſhould magnifie his glorious Name: &amp; if it were poſſible, by ſome vnuſuall ſtrain of our vnited tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, pierce the very skies, &amp; giue an Eccho to thoſe celeſtiall Quires, ſinging Honor, &amp; praiſe, and glory, bee to our gracious God, for all his mercifull deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances both of Prince and people. Yea, O Lord, ſtill preſerue thine own <hi>Annointed:</hi> conuert or confound all his enemies; but vpon his head let his Crown flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Long, long liue that royal keeper of Gods holy Temple, &amp; the <hi>Defender</hi> of that <hi>Faith</hi> which he hath of old giuen to his Saints: and let all true-hearted <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> ſay, <hi>Amen:</hi> yea, let <hi>Amen,</hi> the faithfull witnes in heauen, the <hi>Word</hi> &amp; <hi>Truth</hi> of God, ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it. For our ſelues, let vs heartily repent of our former ſins, religiouſly amend our future liues, abandon all our inteſtine Idols, ſerue the Lord with pure hearts; and ſtill, and ſtill, God ſhall deliuer both Him and vs from all our enemies. This God grant for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> for his merits ſake, the Holy Ghoſt for his Names ſake; to whom, three perſons, and one eternall God, be all praiſe and glory, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and thankſgiuing, world without end.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:521:37"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
